<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Articles on Strange Company - Creating Virtual Worlds For 2 Decades</title>
    <link>http://www.strangecompany.org/articles/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Articles on Strange Company - Creating Virtual Worlds For 2 Decades</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2016 14:26:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.strangecompany.org/articles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>I will now talk about whether VR is an &#34;Empathy Machine&#34; for 12.5 min</title>
      <link>http://www.strangecompany.org/articles/vr-as-empathy-machine/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2016 14:26:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.strangecompany.org/articles/vr-as-empathy-machine/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Various people have suggested that I spend some time talking about Virtual Reality and all the interesting thoughts, challenges, and other bits and pieces around it, on YouTube. So I&amp;rsquo;m giving that a go!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First video: the whole &amp;ldquo;VR as Empathy Machine&amp;rdquo; concept. Is it right? If not, what IS VR?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9&#34;&gt;&lt;iframe class=&#34;embed-responsive-item&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/BOfX19_e33A&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Links for things referenced in the video:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://techcrunch.com/2015/01/23/un-launches-powerful-oculus-virtual-reality-film-following-syrian-refugee-girl/&#34;&gt;Syrian Refugee Experience&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WCprfChibTE&#34;&gt;VR Gender Swap Experience&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GNS_theory&#34;&gt;Gamist, Narrativist and Simulationist RPGs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://papersplea.se/&#34;&gt;Papers Please&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://store.steampowered.com/app/282070/&#34;&gt;This War Of Mine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://store.steampowered.com/app/488760&#34;&gt;Left-Hand Path&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What do you think of the whole &amp;ldquo;Empathy Machine&amp;rdquo; concept? Let me know on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.twitter.com/hughhancock&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/strangecompany&#34;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;, or join the discussion on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/Vive/comments/5y0nx3/i_will_now_talk_about_whether_vr_is_an_empathy/&#34;&gt;Reddit&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=13810587&#34;&gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Video: Testing The Leap Motion In VR. Contains Happy Swearing.</title>
      <link>http://www.strangecompany.org/video-testing-the-leap-motion-in-vr-contains-happy-swearing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2016 14:26:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.strangecompany.org/video-testing-the-leap-motion-in-vr-contains-happy-swearing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As promised, I managed to get longtime SC collaborator &lt;a href=&#34;https://johnnie.me.uk/&#34;&gt;Johnnie Ingram&lt;/a&gt; to test out the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.strangecompany.org/leap-motion-orion-yes-the-leap-works-now/&#34;&gt;Leap Motion&amp;rsquo;s new Orion software&lt;/a&gt; in VR so I could record it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I say &amp;ldquo;I managed&amp;rdquo; - actually he insisted. Forcefully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And his response was&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, let&amp;rsquo;s just say he was impressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9&#34;&gt;&lt;iframe class=&#34;embed-responsive-item&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/nftfaJxJApI&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afterward, Johnnie described the experience as &lt;strong&gt;mind-blowing&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;life-changing&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doesn&amp;rsquo;t quite have the precision to do small or complicated movements. But honestly, when you&amp;rsquo;re playing with it, you don&amp;rsquo;t care. It feels like magic. It&amp;rsquo;s sorcery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;VR is here. It&amp;rsquo;s real. And it&amp;rsquo;s getting better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tried out the Leap with the Orion software yourself? Let me know on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.twitter.com/hughhancock&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/strangecompany&#34;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;, or join the discussion on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/oculus/comments/47cu8r/video_testing_the_leap_motion_orion_software_with/&#34;&gt;Reddit&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=11166918&#34;&gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Film Is Two Artforms, Not One</title>
      <link>http://www.strangecompany.org/theres-not-one-film-industry-there-are-two/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2016 13:47:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.strangecompany.org/theres-not-one-film-industry-there-are-two/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not convinced that the &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;film industry&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; exists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been spending a lot of time thinking about filmmaking in 2016 (as a sort of follow up to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.antipope.org/charlie/blog-static/2015/06/hugh-hancock-here-again-charli.html&#34;&gt;some of my&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.antipope.org/charlie/blog-static/2015/08/a-storm-of-stories---and-what-.html&#34;&gt;previous posts&lt;/a&gt; ). And my conclusion is that it makes very little sense to think of the film industry as a single entity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;industry-the-first&#34;&gt;Industry The First&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s the &lt;strong&gt;studio film industry&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It spends around $60m - $200m per film. It has an effective lock on cinema releases in the UK and US: a studio film will get a cinema release, and will spend some time there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/TeuWkUJ.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Avengers Assemble&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Studio films are artifacts of mass interest and appeal, and are treated as such. Popular blogs assume that the reader is already familiar with them, whether they&amp;rsquo;re &lt;em&gt;Star Wars&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Inside Out&lt;/em&gt;. Newspapers review them by default.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of production, aside from the massive armies of people involved, the key difference is that studio films use &lt;em&gt;massive&lt;/em&gt; amounts of digital special effects, often invisibly. Studio films are evolving into a hybrid of animation and live action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They&amp;rsquo;re also largely a single arm of a multi-tentacled franchise monster, and can often best be considered from a business perspective as a marketing expense for that franchise which will hopefully earn its money back. They don&amp;rsquo;t always make their money back, but taken as part of a larger franchise play and a studio&amp;rsquo;s slate are reliably - not universially, but investably - profitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The studio film has enormous scope, can tell pretty much any story, but is limited by its need to appeal to a wide enough audience to make its money back. That&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; wide audience, to the point that up until recently &amp;ldquo;R&amp;rdquo; rated films - any &amp;ldquo;R&amp;rdquo; rated films - were considered to not appeal widely enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;industry-the-second&#34;&gt;Industry The Second&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there&amp;rsquo;s the &lt;strong&gt;indie film industry&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It spends between $5k and $5m per film. It&amp;rsquo;s almost never a cinema-centric medium: some independent films will have short, limited theater runs, but those are usually intended to raise the film&amp;rsquo;s profile or garner social proof (reviews) that it wouldn&amp;rsquo;t get any other way. If it does have a theater run (and maybe 1 in 10 will), it&amp;rsquo;s expecting to make a loss on that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/3KRsrwb.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Blue Ruin&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primary expected venue for the indie film industry is &lt;em&gt;Video On Demand&lt;/em&gt;. These films are expected to be watched on Netflix, on Amazon Instant, or on cable pay-per-view. That&amp;rsquo;s a totally different venue to a studio film and allows - indeed demands - a different style of storytelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indie films are not at all mass interest or mass appeal films. Films which are regarded in the indie world as massive, unrepeatable breakout hits are niche or minority interest compared to studio films. 20 years ago this wasn&amp;rsquo;t true, but we&amp;rsquo;re discussing the current film world. Compare the profile of a film like &lt;em&gt;Resevoir Dogs&lt;/em&gt; to that of &lt;em&gt;Blue Ruin&lt;/em&gt; (which you may not have heard of  - it&amp;rsquo;s one of the most breakout indies of the last half decade or so).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most indies are completely unknown outside a small target audience. The ones that become profitable - and most don&amp;rsquo;t - often do so by carefully targeting a small underserved niche that mainstream films rarely or never touch and tailoring their story closely to that niche. The biggest of these niches are the LGBT and Christian niches, but there are smaller ones - Joel Paul Reisling, for example, has done rather well targeting $100k movies at the &amp;ldquo;family-friendly girl and horse&amp;rdquo; niche.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indies can&amp;rsquo;t afford to tell an awful lot of stories. Even at the higher end of the budget they&amp;rsquo;re very constrained on practical and digital effects (to the standards required by 2016 audiences), action sequences, number of locations, crowd scenes, and a number of more technical areas. Generally they focus on a story that can be told in a single or small number of locations, with a small number of cast, and extremely limited stunts of any kind, preferably none.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indie films are rarely profitable and often not created with the primary intention of making a profit. They&amp;rsquo;re often made at a loss as a calling card for directors hoping to subsequently make studio films.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;These two faces of the film industry are so very different that I&amp;rsquo;m not convinced it makes any sense to  refer to them as the same artform. For example, indie movies have more in common with theater than they do with studio movies.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;_What do you think? Let me know on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.twitter.com/hughhancock&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/strangecompany&#34;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;, or join the discussion on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/movies/comments/476olw/are_movies_two_seperate_artforms_not_one/&#34;&gt;Reddit&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=11158809&#34;&gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt;._&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Leap Motion ORION: Yes, The Leap Works Now</title>
      <link>http://www.strangecompany.org/leap-motion-orion-yes-the-leap-works-now/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2016 14:03:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.strangecompany.org/leap-motion-orion-yes-the-leap-works-now/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;So, some time ago, a company called LEAP Motion produced a demo video that looked truly incredible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They claimed to have a new piece of technology, a tiny little box, which would track your hands and usher us all into the world of Minority Report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/V5SKXLp.png&#34; alt=&#34;Imgur&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like a lot of folk, I bought one. In my case, I bought one specifically because motion-capturing hands is a Hard Problem: it&amp;rsquo;s possible to get &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yX-6vwRCMnI&#34;&gt;inertial motion capture gloves&lt;/a&gt;, but they&amp;rsquo;re not cheap for $10k values of not cheap, and in my opinion the output quality isn&amp;rsquo;t that good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big day arrived. The LEAP Motion was unboxed. I tested it out, and lo!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn&amp;rsquo;t much cop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wobbly, laggy, inaccurate. Back into the box it went, and that was the last I thought of it. Until two days ago, when the company behind the LEAP - how to put this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaped into action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, in defiance of the normal &amp;ldquo;release, be crap, go bust&amp;rdquo; cycle, the guys and girls behind LEAP have been quietly working away at making it better. And amazingly, they claimed that they&amp;rsquo;d fixed most of its problems without even forcing us to buy a new device. Instead, they just had a new software release called ORION, and they claimed that installing it would make the LEAP work as promised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One frantic dig into the Big Box O&amp;rsquo; Unused Tech in my cupboard later, I was ready to test their claims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-great-leap-forward&#34;&gt;A Great Leap Forward&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two spoilers. One, there are going to be a lot of &amp;ldquo;leap&amp;rdquo; puns in this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two, yep, it works now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not perfectly, for me, so far - it&amp;rsquo;s a little wobbly during the daytime, as the tech might be good, but it uses IR light to track, and there&amp;rsquo;s a damn big IR emitter outside my window which kinda fucks with that during the daytime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, when using it for VR, I heartily recommend clearing your desk before beginning. With a headset-mounted Leap the minimum close tracking distance isn&amp;rsquo;t particularly close. However, it DOES work fine at arm&amp;rsquo;s length. Unless what&amp;rsquo;s sitting at arm&amp;rsquo;s length is an expensive condenser mic, in which case you will a) fail to grab the block you&amp;rsquo;re reaching for and b) punch your microphone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the downside, calibration is about as much fun as it is with most optical devices. For anyone who has never had that particular joy - it&amp;rsquo;s not much fun. Essentially, you wobble the LEAP around and point it at reflective things, waiting for the Magic Software to tell you it&amp;rsquo;s calibrated. The first few times you try it, it won&amp;rsquo;t be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tip if you&amp;rsquo;re doing this - rotate the Leap, don&amp;rsquo;t just move it around. Also, I had to iterate through about three allegedly reflective surfaces to get one that worked - ironically enough I ended up using the screen of my Surface Pro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it&amp;rsquo;s orders of magnitude better than the last time I tried the Leap. I duct-taped it to my Oculus DK2 (the Leap site recommends their proprietory adapter, but if you search around a bit you can find &lt;a href=&#34;https://community.leapmotion.com/t/unofficial-vr-mount-thread/2296&#34;&gt;their unofficial mount thread including duct tape instructions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mine did not look as neat as the one in their official thread, but it worked fine:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/W9Hni8r.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Imgur&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tested out their &amp;ldquo;Blocks&amp;rdquo; app, which allows you to pick up and throw around blocks in a virtual environment, using your hands.  No latency I could feel, and I could throw blocks around and build towers in VR fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very impressed indeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later in the evening, once the irritatingly persistent IR emitter in the sky had gone away, I gave it another shot (whilst also standing up to avoid the punch-the-mic problem). It worked extremely well, even better than before, to the point that I was getting some &amp;ldquo;presence&amp;rdquo; in VR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did try to shoot a short video of the process, but unfortunately the LEAP does rather hog the USB bus, and as a result didn&amp;rsquo;t play at all well with my webcam. So here&amp;rsquo;s a video from someone else who clearly got over the problem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did a bit of more rigorous testing with the LEAP&amp;rsquo;s debug visualiser, trying to find hand positions it didn&amp;rsquo;t like. Amusingly, the only one it seemed to have trouble with was the classic middle-finger-in-air gesture - however, it would appear &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/oculus/comments/46i1o8/that_new_orion_leap_motion_software_seems_to_work/&#34;&gt;that problem&amp;rsquo;s not universal&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It did still struggle a bit with my girlfriend Becca&amp;rsquo;s hands - she has rheumatoid arthritis, and so her hands don&amp;rsquo;t move perfectly and are semi-locked in a position with the back two fingers curved. It did much better than when it was released, but still, the tracking didn&amp;rsquo;t work as well as it did for me. Obviously, this is an edge case, but it&amp;rsquo;d be good to see it improve, particularly given how useful VR is for various accessibility / disability applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately it seems that the LEAP Orion improvements don&amp;rsquo;t carry over to all of the LEAP&amp;rsquo;s app store. I tested out their non-VR sculpting tool as well, but was almost completely unable to get it to play nicely. In short, it seemed to be working about as well as it did before the update.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in the new VR apps, it&amp;rsquo;s extremely cool and very usable. And some of the showcases that we&amp;rsquo;re seeing coming out of the VR community look super-cool - I&amp;rsquo;m particularly looking forward to the various &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aoF3dPNhApU&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&#34;&gt;wizard simulators&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall - this is a remarkable improvement to what was formerly a neat but pretty useless toy. I&amp;rsquo;ll definitely be hooking it up to &lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.leapmotion.com/gallery/hand-capture&#34;&gt;their Motionbuilder plugin&lt;/a&gt; for some testing as soon as I get the chance&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;_Have you tested out the LEAP&amp;rsquo;s new ORION software? Got any tips or suggestions? Feel free to give me a shout on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.twitter.com/hughhancock&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/strangecompany&#34;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; - or join the discussions on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/oculus/comments/46ks2y/thoughts_from_testing_out_the_leap_motion_hand/&#34;&gt;Reddit&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=11133475&#34;&gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt;._&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And if you&amp;rsquo;d like to be updated on what I&amp;rsquo;m doing, testing and making on a semi-regular basis, click this here linky thing.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Realtime Visuals Vs Pre-Rendered: How Close Can I Get?</title>
      <link>http://www.strangecompany.org/realtime-visuals-vs-pre-rendered-how-close-can-i-get/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Feb 2016 12:51:39 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.strangecompany.org/realtime-visuals-vs-pre-rendered-how-close-can-i-get/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;OK, before I begin this, I should mention one very important salient fact: this comparison is specific to one non-photorealistic project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.strangecompany.org/development-notes-unreal-engine-as-a-movie-renderer/&#34;&gt;a couple of days ago&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;rsquo;m looking once again at using realtime engines as movie renderers for my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stoneandsorcery.com&#34;&gt;Stone And Sorcery&lt;/a&gt; project. That&amp;rsquo;s a non-photorealistic animated series, using a strong voxel / Minecraft aesthetic. As such, I wondered just how close I could get to the visuals I achieved using a conventional path tracer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer turns out to be &amp;ldquo;very close, but not without some pain and swearing&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the original image I&amp;rsquo;m trying to copy, from the Stone And Sorcery ads I put out last year. It was rendered in about 4 seconds using 3DSMax - fast for a path tracer, but that still gives us a render time of &lt;strong&gt;8 hours or so&lt;/strong&gt; for each camera angle of a 5-minute short.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.strangecompany.org/media/Stone-And-Sorcery-Website-Image-11.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-progression&#34;&gt;The Progression&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I got started, using Unity 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unity 5 boasts realtime global illumination, using the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.geomerics.com/enlighten/&#34;&gt;Enlighten&lt;/a&gt; engine, but it&amp;rsquo;s only realtime at the user&amp;rsquo;s end. It requires a precomputation step on the part of the creator. Somewhat nervously, I hit the button to start the precomp - but it turns out that on a set this small, it&amp;rsquo;s really quick. About a second or so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(That was significantly &lt;strong&gt;less true&lt;/strong&gt; on a large Minecraft export I tried as an earlier test: the calculation crashed out hard with what I believe is an out-of-memory error. )&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I had basic GI, I remembered roughly the lighting setup I&amp;rsquo;d used, I dug around to find the right textures and normal map (the latter being responsible for the fine detail on the geometry you can see above - amazingly in 2016 Unity still doesn&amp;rsquo;t have displacement maps by default), and I dropped in some &amp;ldquo;make it pretty&amp;rdquo; functions that I assumed would equate to the path tracer&amp;rsquo;s output - bloom, SonicEther&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.assetstore.unity3d.com/en/#!/content/36093&#34;&gt;very nice ambient occlusion plugin&lt;/a&gt;, and depth of field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.strangecompany.org/media/Unity-Goblins-v0.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, it looks kinda nice, but it&amp;rsquo;s clearly not the same. The depth of field looks horrible, the normal maps are jagged, I&amp;rsquo;ve lost the textures on the bow, and the lighting&amp;rsquo;s wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dropping the depth of field like a hot rock - one thing I&amp;rsquo;ll need to do if I keep up this approach is to either abandon depth of field as a cinematic tool or find a much better shader for it -I get this. Immediately significantly better, but still not there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.strangecompany.org/media/unity-Goblins-v1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I went back to the original path-tracing model in Max, and took a careful look at what was going on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For starters, there was some geometry missing in the FBX file I imported - that&amp;rsquo;s what was responsible for the line behind the characters&amp;rsquo; heads in the original. Expecting the fix to be a complete nightmare, I tried the simplest thing I could think of - create a cube, texture it with the ceiling texture, put it in place, all in Unity. Astonishingly, it worked, and matching the texture scales turned out not to be the bear I was anticipating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, the normal maps looked horrible. You can see that at the bottom of the above image, the geometry&amp;rsquo;s all pixelated. This frustrated me for a good long while - I managed to track down the fact that I&amp;rsquo;d got two normal maps on the single texture by mistake, but still, the maps came out pixelated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I dived into Unity&amp;rsquo;s texture detail settings, and found the problem. The original normal maps are extremely high resolution - more than 8k pixels wide. However, Unity is designed for games, which generally don&amp;rsquo;t like images that large (particularly on an iPhone), and so it resizes them by default, and then applies some lossy compression. That&amp;rsquo;s fine if you&amp;rsquo;re not seeing the texture close-up (look at the ceiling), but it&amp;rsquo;s an image-destroyer for something which occupies a quarter of the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I killed every compression, filtering, and size-reduction setting I could see, and the normals returned to close to the quality we see in the path tracer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I just straight-up copied the light colours and placements from the path tracing file, and dropped them in. And I took considerably more care over the exact frame of animation I used&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.strangecompany.org/media/Unity-Goblins-v2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I think we can all agree, it ended up looking like dogshit on toast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up until now, I was starting to think that there was very little difference between the lighting quality in Unity and in MAX, at least for this scene. However, now I hit the big caveat to that theory: Unity can look great, but its lighting &lt;strong&gt;absolutely does not&lt;/strong&gt; behave like a path tracer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lighting settings for the light at the back produced very different colours, for no reason I fully understand. The light also bounced differently, partially because Unity 5&amp;rsquo;s standard shader is a PBR (Physically Based Renderer) shader with completely different settings to the normal diffuse/specular/normal shader in MAX. You can see in the above image that the ceiling is quite shiny, almost plastic-looking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn&amp;rsquo;t copy the shader settings, so I tweaked the Unity shader to look a bit better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another huge issue: whilst in MAX lights can be of an arbitrary size, in Unity the real-time lighting all comes from point sources - sources that are infinitely small. Before last year&amp;rsquo;s journey through the world of Real Film I didn&amp;rsquo;t fully realise the key difference between small sources and large: larger sources produce completely different, much softer shadows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to fake the effect by adding 3 point lights rather than one at the back. At this point the &amp;ldquo;faking it&amp;rdquo; and complexity of game lighting was starting to show through: whilst game lighting might be faster, it&amp;rsquo;s often the case that you need to spend a lot more time working around its limitations than when you&amp;rsquo;re working with a path tracer, which will simply render light exactly as it works in the real world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I had the lighting at the front of the image to contend with. In the path tracer, it&amp;rsquo;s down the bottom of the pit the goblins are looking into: thanks to the magic of inverse-square law, it illuminates the edge more than the ceiling. In Unity, I found, the reverse was true - possibly because I&amp;rsquo;d not set the shader up correctly, or possibly because of a limitation of the more simple lighting model. I ended up having to move the light closer in order to make the ceiling darker and the edge lighter - something that makes no sense, but clearly worked with the lighting model in Unity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thus we end up with the final version:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.strangecompany.org/media/Unity-Goblins-v3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For comparison, here&amp;rsquo;s the original path-traced image again:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.strangecompany.org/media/Stone-And-Sorcery-Website-Image-11.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously the lighting&amp;rsquo;s not precisely right - there&amp;rsquo;s a bit more contrast in the original. The angle&amp;rsquo;s slightly different too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it&amp;rsquo;s pretty close.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Showing the two images to some friends, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.twitter.com/johnnieingram&#34;&gt;Johnnie Ingram&lt;/a&gt; pointed out something very interesting. Due to the nature of the two renderers, the edges in the Unity render are much sharper than those in the path-traced renderer. He felt that a &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; person who didn&amp;rsquo;t know the origin of the two images would think that the Unity render was thus higher quality. It&amp;rsquo;ll be interesting to test!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ambient occlusion effect works nicely in the Unity version to add additional shadow and detail. The only issue there is the green halo around the left-side character&amp;rsquo;s head - apparently the SSAO algorithm used in that particular shader still has trouble identifying objects that are seperate from the background. I know the NVidia HBAO algorithm has less trouble with that - although it has problems of its own - so I&amp;rsquo;ll probably try a variant of that one next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, as a proof of concept this looks pretty solid. Next step is to render the second episode of Stone And Sorcery with Unity and see how it holds up - coming soon!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*If you want to let me know what you think, feel free to give me a shout on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.twitter.com/hughhancock&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/strangecompany&#34;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; - or join the discussions on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/Unity3D/comments/458moy/attempting_to_recreate_prerendered_image_results/&#34;&gt;Reddit&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=11079828&#34;&gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt;. Links will be added once I&amp;rsquo;ve set those up!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First Look: Amazon&#39;s New Games Engine, Lumberyard</title>
      <link>http://www.strangecompany.org/first-look-amazons-new-games-engine-lumberyard/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Feb 2016 10:55:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.strangecompany.org/first-look-amazons-new-games-engine-lumberyard/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I just saw that &lt;a href=&#34;http://aws.amazon.com/lumberyard/&#34;&gt;Amazon have gotten into the games engine business&lt;/a&gt; with a new engine, Lumberyard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve had a look at the documentation and features list - haven&amp;rsquo;t tried to build anything in it yet - and wrote up my thoughts as a &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=11064454&#34;&gt;comment over at Hacker News&lt;/a&gt;. Since that became rather long, I thought I&amp;rsquo;d reproduce it here as an article for others who might be interested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Digging into the details, it seems this is largely a fork or adaption of the CryEngine, with all the advantages and disadvantages that brings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said about Autodesk&amp;rsquo;s offering, Stingray, I think that even a giant like Amazon is going to have an uphill battle bringing a new game engine into mass use. Having been testing game engines just this week, I&amp;rsquo;m reminded just how much of an ecosystem has built up around Unity in particular - displacing an engine with that is like displacing Wordpress as the dominant blogging engine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s early days yet but they&amp;rsquo;ve got some serious catching up to do. For example, it appears that 3D assets can only currently be created in Max and Maya (no Blender, no Cinema4d), as rather than using FBX or similar as an interchange format they&amp;rsquo;re using their own custom formats with an exporter. Most other game engines stopped doing that a while ago, for good reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, the level editor is either underdocumented or feature-light. The docs currently just cover creating terrain and vegetation. I assume that the engine has the capability to handle non-outdoor scenes too, but it&amp;rsquo;s not explicitly documented anywhere I can find in a quick look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s also no documentation on non-sky lighting, lighting builds, light types, or similar that I can find. There&amp;rsquo;s one mention that the engine supports Global Illumination, but no details as to whether it&amp;rsquo;s realtime or requires a bake process. Searching for &amp;ldquo;lighting&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;lights&amp;rdquo;, or &amp;ldquo;light&amp;rdquo; in the documentation returns no results!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, there&amp;rsquo;s a full-featured cinematics system, which means it&amp;rsquo;s of considerable interest to me, but that&amp;rsquo;s very much a minority thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish them luck and I&amp;rsquo;ll certainly be checking it out, having said all that. Another fully open-source (not in the sense of Free And Open Source, but in the sense that the source is all accessible) 3D engine is no bad thing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Development Notes: Unreal Engine As A Movie Renderer</title>
      <link>http://www.strangecompany.org/development-notes-unreal-engine-as-a-movie-renderer/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2016 13:04:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.strangecompany.org/development-notes-unreal-engine-as-a-movie-renderer/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m doing a lot of ongoing research at the moment into &lt;strong&gt;new production techniques&lt;/strong&gt; for live-action, animation, and comics, and will be writing some of that up here in semi-note form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the first of those!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at the possibility of using the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.unrealengine.com&#34;&gt;Unreal Engine&lt;/a&gt; as a movie renderer in 2016, I&amp;rsquo;ve come to the conclusion that it&amp;rsquo;s possible, but not the slam-dunk awesome solution it initially seemed it might be. So here are my thoughts on that, and future directions for research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-theory&#34;&gt;The theory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why would I &lt;strong&gt;even consider&lt;/strong&gt; using a game engine as a renderer, given the toolchain issues?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(For non-animators: basically, you want to have as few programs in your critical path from &amp;ldquo;I have an idea&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;I have a movie&amp;rdquo; as possible. Using a game engine rather than just rendering in a 3D program adds at least one, which is bad, and usually a bunch of non-trivial export problems too.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the kind of non-photoreal animation I&amp;rsquo;m currently looking at (below), &lt;strong&gt;current-gen game engines produce visuals that are more than adequate for my needs&lt;/strong&gt;. And, obviously, they render far, far faster than even GPU-accelerated conventional 3D renderers - 75ms per frame compared to a second or two per frame. That equals a lot more flexibility in production, and a lot less waiting around for 200 frames to re-render because you didn&amp;rsquo;t spot a character&amp;rsquo;s hand goes through the wall for a few seconds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/8nFdh5O.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even second-to-two-second render times really start to mount up on most productions. So, if you can simply take animated assets from Motionbuilder or Max straight into Unreal, set up a camera, and render out in realtime, that could be an incredibly freeing workflow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what doesn&amp;rsquo;t work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-practise&#34;&gt;The Practise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, whilst the Unreal Engine has massively improved its import pipeline, it&amp;rsquo;s still not the most user-friendly thing on the planet. I hit the usual problems of incompatibilities, unintelligible error messages (mostly references to non-existent bones) and wildly varying scales between 3D scenes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of these are close to being a dealbreaker. In all cases, they&amp;rsquo;re solve-once-solve-forever issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big hairy problem, though, is the time it takes to import a 3D asset - specifically, an animation. Importing a relatively simple 20 second or so mocap file took about 5 minutes on my computer. Bigger ones seemed to take longer - before crashing (although I imagine that&amp;rsquo;s fixable).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that you&amp;rsquo;ll have to redo that import every time you want to make a change to the animation, that&amp;rsquo;s a big timesink, and really diminishes the utility of this approach compared to &amp;ldquo;just render in Max&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then we hit the lighting. Simple directional lighting is indeed truly realtime, but to get sophisticated lighting results including global illumination, indirect bounce light, and so on, Unreal Engine is still dependent - as far as I can tell - on the age-old &amp;ldquo;bake the lightmap&amp;rdquo; approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means, essentially, that we still have a render stage. It&amp;rsquo;s quite a fast one, and it only needs to be done once before the realtime render can kick in, but still, it&amp;rsquo;s another significant slowdown - and apparently one that on larger maps can get quite slow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between the two, it looks like the choice between render-in-Max and render-in-game-engine is actually pretty much a dead heat. And then it comes down to the choice of tools available- at which point the fact that Unreal&amp;rsquo;s designed to make games, and Max is designed to animate things, really means that Max has the edge. (Even if I do still hate Max&amp;rsquo;s animation interface compared to Motionbuilder.) Matinee, Unreal&amp;rsquo;s cinematics tool, is sadly still about as friendly as a 2002 Avid workstation stapled to an angry grizzly bear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/0ESRpOd.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Imgur&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there we have it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;future-directions-for-testing&#34;&gt;Future Directions For Testing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t think that Unity would provide much better results, although I should test it now that it has its swanky new lighting engine. Certainly last time I used Unity the import pipeline was a lot less painful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stingray, Autodesk&amp;rsquo;s own game engine, might also be an option, but from reading around, their cinematics interface is even less friendly, requiring 20 minutes of scripting just to render out a movie. Nuts to that, quite frankly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Unreal&amp;rsquo;s import pipeline gets much faster, it&amp;rsquo;ll definitely be worth checking out again. In particular, if they add &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alembic_(Computer_Graphics)&#34;&gt;Alembic&lt;/a&gt; support that&amp;rsquo;d change things a lot - assuming that it imported reasonably fast - but it appears to have been on the wishlist for years with no sign of movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, of course, I should once again check out Maya&amp;rsquo;s realtime preview window, which last time I tested it looked to provide the best of game engine and animation package, but then failed by being spectacularly buggy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If only Autodesk would just weld a decent 3D renderer onto Motionbuilder. Then I could just use that and carry on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-unity&#34;&gt;UPDATE: Unity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unity testing is somewhat more promising. In particular, lengthy FBX animations import pretty much instantly, removing one of the biggest roadblocks I was concerned about above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unity doesn&amp;rsquo;t have built-in camera movement support (although apparently it&amp;rsquo;s coming soon) or movie export support, so the next job is to test solutions for both of those.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, the lighting bake problem is still concerning. I need to test it on a smaller map, but tested on an admittedly large and heavy voxel map, it was extremely slow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s possible to just use realtime solutions, but they&amp;rsquo;re pretty ugly - about the visual fidelity of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.deathknightlovestory.com&#34;&gt;Death Knight Love Story&lt;/a&gt; or below. Having said that, I used a renderer with that level of capability for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MhDJxESBiJo&#34;&gt;The Shy Creeper&lt;/a&gt;, which was pretty popular - maybe this is a &amp;ldquo;perfect enemy of good&amp;rdquo; moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, there&amp;rsquo;s a promising realtime GI solution in the Unity Asset Store, so that&amp;rsquo;s the next test to do&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have thoughts, comments or suggestions, please do let me know on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.twitter.com/hughhancock&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/strangecompany&#34;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;, or the discussions on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/gamedev/comments/44r4k6/game_engines_as_movie_renderers_in_2016_comments/&#34;&gt;Reddit&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=11058249&#34;&gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Hacking VFX&#34; at Raindance - Resources Post</title>
      <link>http://www.strangecompany.org/hacking-vfx-at-raindance-resources-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2015 11:20:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.strangecompany.org/hacking-vfx-at-raindance-resources-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Thanks to everyone who came along to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://calendar.raindancefestival.org/films/hacking-hollywood-style-vfx&#34;&gt;Hacking Hollywood VFX&lt;/a&gt; panel at Raindance on Tuesday!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During that talk I mentioned that I&amp;rsquo;d put up a resources post with a bunch of the videos we all talked about during the panel - here they are!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, here are details for our panelists:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0002660/&#34;&gt;Paddy Eason&amp;rsquo;s IMDB entry&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nvizible.com/&#34;&gt;Nvisible&amp;rsquo;s website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/name/nm3426117/&#34;&gt;Damien Valentine&amp;rsquo;s IMDB entry&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bathtub-productions.com/&#34;&gt;Bathtub Productions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Strange_Company&#34;&gt;My Wikipedia entry&lt;/a&gt; (my IMDB is horribly out of date). You&amp;rsquo;re already on my website, but &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.strangecompany.org/movies/&#34;&gt;here&amp;rsquo;s my filmography&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.twitter.com/hughhancock&#34;&gt;my Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mentioned a greenscreen tutorial during the panel - since then I&amp;rsquo;ve actually found another really great one, so here are TWO greenscreen tutorials. Note that as Paddy said on the panel, 90% of the advice relates to the shoot, not post-production!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also talked about the Game Of Thrones VFX breakdowns, which are really fantastic. Here you go:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://vimeo.com/104403406&#34;&gt;Game of Thrones, Season 4 - VFX breakdown&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&#34;https://vimeo.com/rodeofx&#34;&gt;Rodeo FX&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;https://vimeo.com&#34;&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paddy talked about some more indie movies that he&amp;rsquo;s been working on recently - here&amp;rsquo;s an article on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.artofvfx.com/grabbers-paddy-eason-superviseur-vfx-nvizible/&#34;&gt;the VFX of &amp;ldquo;Grabbers&lt;/a&gt; and one on &lt;a href=&#34;http://cinefex.com/blog/robot-overlords/&#34;&gt;the making of Robot Overlords&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s Damien&amp;rsquo;s great cosplay-with-effects video - the effects are in the latter half:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the test I did of 3D camera tracking that convinced me to get into live-action. This took a couple of hours:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://vimeo.com/117587153&#34;&gt;Desk Zombie&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&#34;https://vimeo.com/strangecompany&#34;&gt;Strange Company&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;https://vimeo.com&#34;&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll keep updating this post as I remember more things, and please do ask if there&amp;rsquo;s anything specific you wanted an example of!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Guest-posting: &#34;A Storm Of Stories&#34;</title>
      <link>http://www.strangecompany.org/guest-posting-a-storm-of-stories/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 10:27:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.strangecompany.org/guest-posting-a-storm-of-stories/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The common response to creative types panicking about the mass of content that&amp;rsquo;s being produced right now is &amp;ldquo;Oh, don&amp;rsquo;t worry, it&amp;rsquo;s all crap. If you make something great it&amp;rsquo;ll rise to the top&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But is that true? Once again, science fiction author Charles Stross invited me to blog over at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.antipope.org/charlie/blog-static/&#34;&gt;his uber-popular site&lt;/a&gt;. For this one I decided to dig into the figures for films, TV, books and games. And what I found was both surprising and, frankly, terrifying&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We might assume that getting a really positive response from consumers will still lift you above the masses - indeed, I&amp;rsquo;ve heard the argument time and time again that no really good games, films, books, etc are being ignored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But a very brief look through the lists of media I&amp;rsquo;ve found above puts the lie to that. For example, how many of us have watched The Algerian, a massively-acclaimed, complex international spy thriller with a string of film festival awards? It&amp;rsquo;s right up my alley and I&amp;rsquo;d never heard of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about Over The Garden Wall, a dark animated series in the style of &amp;ldquo;Adventure Time&amp;rdquo;, starring the voices of Elijah Wood and Christopher Lloyd amongst others? Reviews are dribblingly enthusiastic, with an average rating of 9.2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or Tomb Of Tyrants, a fascinating pattern-match / strategy cross-over game with 98% positive reviews on Steam and a small but very dedicated community?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The backlog of genuinely fantastic storytelling that you&amp;rsquo;ve never heard of - and often no-one really heard of - and so quite often the creator&amp;rsquo;s no longer creating or unable to get funding - is only going to grow, and it&amp;rsquo;ll grow fast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.antipope.org/charlie/blog-static/2015/08/a-storm-of-stories---and-what-.html&#34;&gt;Read more »&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Guest-Blogging: 3 CGI Techniques Even Indie Filmmakers Can Use</title>
      <link>http://www.strangecompany.org/guest-blogging-3-cgi-techniques-even-indie-filmmakers-can-use/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Aug 2015 12:45:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.strangecompany.org/guest-blogging-3-cgi-techniques-even-indie-filmmakers-can-use/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was very flattered recently when Elliot Grove, founder of the UK&amp;rsquo;s Raindance film festival and general indie filmmaking legend, asked me to guest-blog over on the Raindance site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it&amp;rsquo;s now up! I&amp;rsquo;m looking at the same tipping point for filmmaking technology that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.strangecompany.org/why-the-guy-who-coined-machinima-is-now-making-live-action-films/&#34;&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been discussing recently on here&lt;/a&gt;, but this time with a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.raindance.org/3-cost-effective-cgi-techniques/&#34;&gt;very practical slant toward fellow indie filmmakers&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s tremendously easy these days to composite elements of stock footage into your shots. And this can be astonishingly powerful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best use of stock footage compositing I&amp;rsquo;ve seen recently was in the TV show Orphan Black. At one point, a character&amp;rsquo;s attempting to flee another character who has a gun, into a cornfield. Firing guns on set is expensive, as we all know; and in this case it wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have served the scene. Instead, they simply cut to a wide shot, then had a gunshot go off – and some birds fly up, startled by the shot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, it&amp;rsquo;s possible that those were real birds. But if it was me shooting that scene, I&amp;rsquo;d definitely have just composited in the bird footage. It completes the shot, and turns a static video of a cornfield into a moment of high drama.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are a few ways you can use this technique, which takes minutes, to add production value or allow you to shoot scenes that otherwise wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be possible&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.raindance.org/3-cost-effective-cgi-techniques/&#34;&gt;Read The Rest Here »&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Will We Soon Be Able To Generate Photo-Realistic Films On Demand? A Reality Check</title>
      <link>http://www.strangecompany.org/will-we-soon-be-able-to-generate-photo-realistic-films-on-demand-a-reality-check/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2015 15:06:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.strangecompany.org/will-we-soon-be-able-to-generate-photo-realistic-films-on-demand-a-reality-check/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;A little while ago I saw a fascinating comment on &lt;a href=&#34;http://news.ycombinator.com&#34;&gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt;, echoing a sentiment that I&amp;rsquo;ve seen around the tech community as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  
&gt; 
&gt; Within a few years, video games will be generating photo-realistic feature films on demand, with unique scripts and characters and worlds adapted to the viewer&#39;s tastes and mood.
&gt; 
&gt; 
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=9960738&#34;&gt;Original comment here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve spent the last 20 years attempting to figure out how to generate as much as possible of the movie-making process in a computer game - with successes including a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bloodspell.com&#34;&gt;well-received feature film&lt;/a&gt; made using computer games tech and feature-length work for companies like Electronic Arts. So I may possibly be the best person in the world to comment on this particular statement, and it&amp;rsquo;s one of considerable interest to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I originally wrote a lengthy reply to his comment on HN, and I&amp;rsquo;m going to expand on it here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s take the statement piece by piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;photo-realistic&#34;&gt;Photo-Realistic&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.strangecompany.org/media/Final-fantasy-3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First thing to note: over the last 30 years, real-time 3D technology - games technology, in other words - has consistently lagged behind the state of the art in non-realtime CGI by approximately 15 years. The first true 3D real-time humanoid-based engine (Quake) happened about 13 years after the first 3D film (The Works). Right now, Total War: Warhammer is producing visuals that are a bit, but not too far, behind the mass-battle scenes of Lord of The Rings. And so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that, if we were able to produce photorealistic humans right now, we&amp;rsquo;d expect realtime photorealism to be about 15 years away. Spoiler: we can&amp;rsquo;t. Whilst we can produce remarkable &lt;a href=&#34;http://imgur.com/a/hrnF8#8&#34;&gt;still images&lt;/a&gt; and even short 20-30 second clips, we&amp;rsquo;ve yet to see anything approaching a successful feature film with a photorealistic CGI human as the star. We can do &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eq1sTNGDXo0&#34;&gt;apes&lt;/a&gt; very well, but humans are still a considerable distance off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can say with considerable certainty that the quality of current realtime CGI characters is definitely nowhere near good enough. In fact, I&amp;rsquo;ve recently &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.strangecompany.org/why-the-guy-who-coined-machinima-is-now-making-live-action-films/&#34;&gt;stopped creating real-time CGI films&lt;/a&gt; after nearly 20 years doing that because the current state of the art appears to be right at the bottom of the Uncanny Valley - about where pre-rendered CGI was &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/final_fantasy_the_spirits_within/&#34;&gt;15 years ago&lt;/a&gt;, in fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;films-on-demand&#34;&gt;Films On Demand&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://savasplace.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/12/moviestorm.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So is an AI director and editor plausible?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ignoring the script, yes, it&amp;rsquo;s possible. We&amp;rsquo;re not there yet but we&amp;rsquo;re getting there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Programmatic editing is a major growth sector right now, as people take gigabytes of holiday video footage and then can&amp;rsquo;t face editing it down. Having &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kamikazecookery.com&#34;&gt;edited massive piles of footage for documentary-style content&lt;/a&gt; in the past, I can empathise. There are a number of startups all competing in this space, but probably the most promising one is &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=9922414&#34;&gt;Shred&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Editing doc-style footage is arguably a harder problem than editing narrative footage, at least to baseline competency levels. A few years of serious effort could probably make this happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Directing, DOP and camerawork is another area where a lot of research has taken place over the years. It hasn&amp;rsquo;t gone much beyond the academic sector thanks to lack of demand. Generally directors like to direct, and camerawork in game cutscenes is fast enough compared to the rest of the process that the research time probably isn&amp;rsquo;t worth it. But in principle it&amp;rsquo;s not too different to constructing a sophisticated FPS bot. I&amp;rsquo;d mark this one down as &amp;ldquo;probably doable&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However - and this is a &lt;strong&gt;big&lt;/strong&gt; however - there is a huge difference between workmanlike directing and artistic, high-quality directing. You can probably get the equivalent of a bad soap opera out of a program in the near future - but getting a program to produce the equivalent of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vulture.com/2013/02/how-master-dp-roger-deakins-got-these-10-shots.html&#34;&gt;Roger Deakins&amp;rsquo; work as a cinematographer&lt;/a&gt; is in the &amp;ldquo;computer that creates art&amp;rdquo; problem pile. It may well require strong AI. If that happens, well, computer-generated films will not be the #1 topic of conversation&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;characters&#34;&gt;Characters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://img15.hostingpics.net/pics/3240117C5jgon.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Procedurally generating human character models, assuming you&amp;rsquo;ve solved the photorealism problem, is pretty easy. You can do it with Daz3D, Maya, and a MEL script.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Procedurally generating them to fit a specific role, however, is far harder. My best guess would be that you could get somewhere by giving the computer some specific rules to follow - strong jaw for action heroes, big eyes for romantic heroine - but I&amp;rsquo;ve no idea how effective that would be. Alternatively, we could give a regret-based algorithm a bunch of adjectives and feed the results to a panel of Mechanical Turkers who say how close the algorithm has gotten to the desired result. That might well work really well, but that&amp;rsquo;s largely because top-end machine learning is scary. Or it might work very well 75% of the time and produce hideous deformed monstrosities the other 25%. It&amp;rsquo;s very hard to tell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Procedurally generating the characters&amp;rsquo; motion, and particularly the characters&amp;rsquo; &lt;strong&gt;emotion&lt;/strong&gt;, is closing on being impossible with current technology. You can get to Sims levels of generation pretty easily, but the looping animations and lack of characterisation are very obvious there. Getting beyond that to genuinely unique motion is very hard, but is an active area of interest for game developers at the moment: the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=r6F3lT1v79I&#34;&gt;Euphoria engine&lt;/a&gt; can produce some very impressive results in a limited range of circumstances, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gdcvault.com/play/1020583/Animation-Bootcamp-An-Indie-Approach&#34;&gt;some indie game developers are pushing procedural animation as far as it will go&lt;/a&gt; (seriously, watch, it&amp;rsquo;s a fascinating talk).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this is still very early-stages stuff. Most procedural animation works by modifying existing animations rather than creating them from scratch, and there&amp;rsquo;s very little discussion of &lt;strong&gt;performance&lt;/strong&gt; - as in an actor&amp;rsquo;s performance - in this tech. Again, we might be able to get to a very wooden actor using a combination of a massive mocap library and procedural animation, but getting to the Sir Ian McKellen simulator might require a theory of mind or strong AI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;worlds&#34;&gt;Worlds&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.strangecompany.org/media/Terrain-With-Trees.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Procedural world generation is very promising right now. Of course, almost everyone is aware that it&amp;rsquo;s possible to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.minecraft.com&#34;&gt;procedurally generate stunning landscapes&lt;/a&gt;, albeit blocky ones. I&amp;rsquo;ve &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.strangecompany.org/im-developing-a-new-way-to-make-films-again/&#34;&gt;experimented extensively&lt;/a&gt; with using procedural generation for films, up to and including doing some &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stoneandsorcery.com&#34;&gt;Minecraft-a-like&lt;/a&gt; work, and it&amp;rsquo;s got massive promise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Procedural generation is already used extensively in film CGI - it&amp;rsquo;s pretty much the raison d&amp;rsquo;etre of expensive, high-end 3D package Houdini. And programs like &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.world-machine.com/&#34;&gt;World Machine&lt;/a&gt; allow the user to create massive, complex landscapes very rapidly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it still requires direction and tweaking. It&amp;rsquo;s possible to see how a procedural script could take a rough animatic with areas marked &amp;ldquo;trees&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;mountain&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;city&amp;rdquo; and effectively act as a &amp;ldquo;make pretty&amp;rdquo; button, but creating sets from just a script direction is much harder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;unique-scripts-adapted-to-the-viewer-s-taste-and-mood&#34;&gt;Unique Scripts Adapted To The Viewer&amp;rsquo;s Taste And Mood&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally we hit the crunch point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recommending films based on the viewer&amp;rsquo;s taste and mood is certainly very doable, and we can even start to generate projects based on data-driven demand. Famously, that&amp;rsquo;s how &amp;ldquo;House Of Cards&amp;rdquo; came to be: when Netflix went datamining, they found that people who like political thrillers also like David Fincher and Kevin Spacey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But a program that can write a script? Nope, we&amp;rsquo;re nowhere with that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generative text is hot right now. There&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/subredditsimulator&#34;&gt;subreddit entirely devoted to computer-generated Reddit posting&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/technology/2014/sep/12/artificial-intelligence-data-journalism-media&#34;&gt;Computerised reporters&lt;/a&gt; are gaining steam. But all the efforts here are still pretty primitive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that&amp;rsquo;s just teaching a computer to write intelligible text. Teaching it to write a story is altogether harder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s NaNoGenMo, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theverge.com/2014/11/25/7276157/nanogenmo-robot-author-novel&#34;&gt;AI Generated Novel equivalent to NaNoRiMo&lt;/a&gt;, but nearly all the generated novels are based on hacks rather than anything actually creating a story structure. There are also researchers - a lot of them - working on generating stories on computer, but so far, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/books/2014/nov/11/can-computers-write-fiction-artificial-intelligence&#34;&gt;their work is extremely primitive&lt;/a&gt;. Scheherazade, one of the most sophisticated programs, produces descriptions of everyday activities - it&amp;rsquo;s considered successful when &amp;ldquo; “people will read the story and recognise the activity and not find too many obvious errors&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, there&amp;rsquo;s no evidence that it&amp;rsquo;s possible to generate a narrative using a computer, let alone write a script, let alone write a script that hits the notes the viewer requires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in short, we might be looking at Hollywood being replaced completely at some point, but I doubt it&amp;rsquo;ll happen in the next 20 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, what IS a huge threat to Hollywood is the increased power of indie filmmakers with technological assists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One filmmaker today can do things that would have required a crew of 20 back in 1993. The cost of filmmaking is plummeting. And that certainly is a threat to Hollywood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s where I&amp;rsquo;m focusing my efforts at the moment - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.strangecompany.org/why-the-guy-who-coined-machinima-is-now-making-live-action-films/&#34;&gt;becoming a cyborg filmmaker&lt;/a&gt;, as it were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to follow how that goes, hit the button below to get updated as I progress!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Guest-Posting: &#34;Ia, Ia, Google Fthagn&#34; and &#34;Any Sufficiently Advanced Technology Is Indistinguishable From Cthulhu&#34;</title>
      <link>http://www.strangecompany.org/guest-posting-ia-ia-google-fthagn-and-any-sufficiently-advanced-technology-is-indistinguishable-from-cthulhu/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2015 13:16:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.strangecompany.org/guest-posting-ia-ia-google-fthagn-and-any-sufficiently-advanced-technology-is-indistinguishable-from-cthulhu/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What would the Cthulhu Mythos look like if they were written from scratch in 2015?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s the question I&amp;rsquo;m answering over on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.antipope.org/charlie/blog-static/&#34;&gt;Charles Stross&amp;rsquo;s blog&lt;/a&gt; today, in a post entitled &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.antipope.org/charlie/blog-static/2015/07/ia-ia-google-fthagn.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Ia, Ia, Google Fthagn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovecraft&amp;rsquo;s concern was vast, alien entities who have no knowledge of, or concern for, the human race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our modern-day concerns are about vast, alien entities who have &lt;strong&gt;total, invasive, privacy-destroying knowledge&lt;/strong&gt; of the minutae of the human race - and still have no concern for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the era of Google, Facebook, datamining and intelligent advertising, the problem isn&amp;rsquo;t that the alien entities who scare the crap out of us have no interest in us - rather the reverse. The aliens in our midst know when we&amp;rsquo;ve become accidentally pregnant. They know what pornography we watch. They can predict our behaviour and influence us to do what they want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this element actually fits rather well into the Cthulhu Mythos&amp;rsquo; core concepts - and it makes them a whole lot scarier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is a sequel of sorts to another piece I wrote on Charlie&amp;rsquo;s blog a couple of weeks back, entitled &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.antipope.org/charlie/blog-static/2015/07/any-sufficiently-advanced-tech.html&#34;&gt;Any Sufficiently Advanced Technology Is Indistinguishable From Cthulhu&lt;/a&gt; -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charlie&amp;rsquo;s Laundry is inspired by the British civil service, spy novels and programming. HOWTO&amp;rsquo;s universe centres around a shady Internet forum where people who would otherwise be doing black-hat SEO crowdsource ways to profit from demonology. And I&amp;rsquo;m sure there are dozens of other spins on the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why does it work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, for starters, the Lovecraftian universe fits extremely well with the universe as understood by geeks. It&amp;rsquo;s a fundementally science-driven place, where all magic is indeed just sufficiently advanced technology. Cthulhu isn&amp;rsquo;t scary because he&amp;rsquo;s a big squid, he&amp;rsquo;s scary because he&amp;rsquo;s a Culture Mind without the sense of humour or concern for human life. Yog-Sothoth isn&amp;rsquo;t a Judeo-Christian demon, it&amp;rsquo;s a force of the universe like Weak Nuclear or gravity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lessons I Learned From My First Live-Action Short (After Nearly 20 Years Of Animation)</title>
      <link>http://www.strangecompany.org/lessons-i-learned-from-my-first-live-action-short-after-nearly-20-years-of-animation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2015 11:46:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.strangecompany.org/lessons-i-learned-from-my-first-live-action-short-after-nearly-20-years-of-animation/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;So, last week I released my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.strangecompany.org/howto-demon-summoning-out-now/&#34;&gt;first-ever live action narrative film project&lt;/a&gt;. And this week I&amp;rsquo;m going to try something a bit different in my blogging (for me, anyway): a write up of the lessons I learned during the course of the film&amp;rsquo;s production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.strangecompany.org/media/BTS-HOWTO-2-e1437565428512.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;BTS-HOWTO-2&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some context:&lt;/strong&gt; I&amp;rsquo;ve been producing animation for nearly 20 years at this point. My work&amp;rsquo;s been featured on CNN, discussed in the New York Times and reviewed by Roger Ebert (which was very cool). But I&amp;rsquo;ve avoided live-action up until now as too clunky, preferring to focus on innovative approaches to animation like &amp;lsquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Machinima&#34;&gt;Machinima&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo; techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was until this year, when a combination of advice from film sales expert &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.filmspecific.com/public/department86.cfm&#34;&gt;Stacey Parks&lt;/a&gt; and my &lt;strong&gt;increasing awareness of advances in film technology&lt;/strong&gt; – &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.strangecompany.org/why-the-guy-who-coined-machinima-is-now-making-live-action-films/&#34;&gt;see my blog post from a couple of weeks ago&lt;/a&gt; – pushed me into acquiring kit and going all-out for live action this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far this year I&amp;rsquo;ve actually shot 3 live action shorts, plus &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.strangecompany.org/some-non-narrative-pieces-from-learning-live-action/&#34;&gt;some non-narrative &amp;lsquo;pretty stuff&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt; (which I&amp;rsquo;ll talk about in another post if folks are interested). But &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.strangecompany.org/howto-demon-summoning-out-now/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;HOWTO: Demon Summoning&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was the first live action narrative feature that I&amp;rsquo;ve finished, and it was also the first one I shot – back in February, in fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it&amp;rsquo;s had a very, very good reception. Stunningly good, actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;174 upvotes on YouTube for a pretty staggering 97.7% positive feedback there.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Positive feedback from reddit, from Facebook, from Twitter and from blogs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s gone far better than I expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was also a pretty fantastic learning experience. So, here are some of the things that I, &amp;lsquo;The Machinima Guy&amp;rsquo;, learned as I took my first tiptoe steps into the &lt;strong&gt;scary world of Real Life Film&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to focus on the filming aspect here. Marketing and release are a different beast, and I might write a post about them in future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;people-are-way-more-forgiving-of-live-action-than-animation&#34;&gt;People Are Way More Forgiving Of Live Action Than Animation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.strangecompany.org/media/Still-6-e1437565377550.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Still-6&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working in animation, you&amp;rsquo;re held to an extremely high standard by virtually all viewers; even non-technical, non-industry viewers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lipsynch doesn&amp;rsquo;t look perfect? Your film&amp;rsquo;s shit. There&amp;rsquo;s a jitter for five frames in one shot? Your film&amp;rsquo;s shit. One background character looks a bit pixelated? Yeah, you guessed it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve spent a long time – about the last 5 years before this year – trying to push &lt;strong&gt;the quality of my animation&lt;/strong&gt; up to the point where it&amp;rsquo;s acceptable to the general viewing public, and I&amp;rsquo;ve never quite hit that point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe that&amp;rsquo;s because the only animation that most people see is produced by Pixar or Dreamworks, and they set a pretty high bar. Or maybe it&amp;rsquo;s the dreaded &amp;lsquo;Uncanny Valley&amp;rsquo;, and the better my work has gotten the deeper into the Valley it&amp;rsquo;s sunk. Certainly it&amp;rsquo;s true that the audience was more critical of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.deathknightlovestory.com&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Death Knight Love Story&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; than they were of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bloodspell.com&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;BloodSpell&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, despite the fact that the latter looked a &lt;strong&gt;lot&lt;/strong&gt; more primitive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I was pretty nervous releasing my first live action film – a film which, I knew, wasn&amp;rsquo;t shot anywhere close to Hollywood standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the response was really surprising. People didn&amp;rsquo;t pick up on or get distracted by the production values. Even when the exposure was a bit ropey, there was noise in the shot, or in one case our actor was visibly wearing an earphone for his lines, no one minded. ALL the comments I&amp;rsquo;ve had about the cinematography and lighting have been positive, despite the fact that I was a massive n00b at the time of production and, if I&amp;rsquo;m being 100% honest, some of &lt;em&gt;HOWTO&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/em&gt; shots make me wince now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, the only negative comments I&amp;rsquo;ve had – aside from a couple of &amp;lsquo;didn&amp;rsquo;t get on with the story&amp;rsquo; comments and one or two &amp;lsquo;editing could have been tighter&amp;rsquo; mentions – were &lt;strong&gt;about the CGI character&lt;/strong&gt;. Several viewers mentioned that small things about his appearance took them out of the film. The Uncanny Valley strikes again&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a post-script: another possible reason why viewers were more forgiving is that my previous films have been heavily drama-based, and &lt;em&gt;HOWTO&lt;/em&gt; is very much a comedy-horror. However, that&amp;rsquo;s not the case with all my upcoming shorts, so we&amp;rsquo;ll see how they go down!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;you-can-now-shoot-a-film-lit-by-four-candles&#34;&gt;You can now shoot a film lit by four candles.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.strangecompany.org/media/Still-22-e1437565462927.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Still-22&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the big reasons I avoided live action for so long was because of the lighting. I knew it was a nightmare. I knew because I&amp;rsquo;d been told by friends with film experience, I knew because I&amp;rsquo;d read about how to do live action lighting in books, and I knew because it had been a PITA on my lo-fi cooking show &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kamikazecookery.com&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kamikaze Cookery&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when I read about and subsequently &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=q8qmccMniSI&#34;&gt;saw&lt;/a&gt; the power of the Sony A7S camera to shoot using very low light (in film terms, that is), I was pretty excited. And with &lt;em&gt;HOWTO&lt;/em&gt;, I decided to push it as far as it would go and shot the first half of the film lit by four tealights only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Result? The tealights kicked ass. Indeed, the only problem we had with those shots was when I panicked and added an additional light, the light from which subsequently bounced off the wall and meant that Johnnie, my lead actor, was the least-lit thing in shot. Derp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had I just trusted the Power Of The Tealight (and modern low-light cameras), everything would have been fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the film was shot using a couple of small, battery-powered LED lights, not even on stands – one was sat on the floor, one was clamped to a bookcase. Again, they provided more than enough light. In fact, my primary challenge was avoiding them over-lighting the background. (I failed in that somewhat, and have now invested in a roll of &amp;lsquo;blackwrap&amp;rsquo; – the pro solution for cutting out light – for future productions.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;physical-shooting-is-exhausting&#34;&gt;Physical shooting is exhausting.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.strangecompany.org/media/BTS-HOWTO-1-e1437565492455.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;BTS-HOWTO-1&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a reasonably fit guy. I&amp;rsquo;m not a Crossfit champion or anything, but I&amp;rsquo;ve been reasonably athletic most of my life, trained in various martial arts, I&amp;rsquo;ve just started weight-training with kettlebells, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of which is a preamble to saying: shooting day kicked the crap out of me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We didn&amp;rsquo;t work insane hours. That&amp;rsquo;s something I&amp;rsquo;m being very careful to avoid: whilst I know the conventional film industry regularly works 14-20 hour days, I&amp;rsquo;d prefer to avoid copying their insanity. (Millions of dollars have been sunk into a number of studies proving that working like that is a Really Really Bad Idea. I don&amp;rsquo;t know why people keep doing it.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We weren&amp;rsquo;t hefting around massive weights. I saved that for &lt;em&gt;Dangerous Treasures&lt;/em&gt;, the &amp;lsquo;Lessons Learned&amp;rsquo; for which will involve the phrase &amp;lsquo;200 kg of plasterboard&amp;rsquo;. But still, I was exhausted for days after the two evenings of shooting; far more so than I expected to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that the extreme tiredness I&amp;rsquo;ve experienced after shoots is significantly a factor of the ultra-lightweight &amp;lsquo;run and gun&amp;rsquo; approach I&amp;rsquo;m aiming for on my live action films. Rather than bring in an entire crew – which has its benefits, but slows production down (once again, this is a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Peopleware-Productive-Projects-Second-Edition/dp/0932633439&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Peopleware&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; issue) – I&amp;rsquo;m working with as small a crew as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On &lt;em&gt;HOWTO&lt;/em&gt;, there were two of us – Ian, on sound, and I –  plus Paul Hamilton, who played Qulkazeth, helping out when he wasn&amp;rsquo;t in shot. It works very well as a fast-moving set, but it does mean that I&amp;rsquo;m keeping a hell of a lot of things in my head at any one time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, whilst the work isn&amp;rsquo;t too physically onerous – nothing compared to an hour of Muay Thai, for example – it&amp;rsquo;s continuous. As director/producer/DoP/caterer/1st AD/everything else, I basically didn&amp;rsquo;t stop moving for 5-8 hours. That took considerably more of a toll the next day – and the next week – than I expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which isn&amp;rsquo;t to say it wasn&amp;rsquo;t awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;it-was-awesome&#34;&gt;It was awesome&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.strangecompany.org/media/BTS-HOWTO-3-e1437565512613.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;BTS-HOWTO-3&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here&amp;rsquo;s the final point. The shoot was tremendously good fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far my experience has been that pre-production is stressful. Post-production is slow. But production is brilliant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve actually had much the same experience before on animation. When we were making &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bloodspell.com&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;BloodSpell&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the &amp;lsquo;animation&amp;rsquo; was entirely produced by 3 or 4 of us in a room, puppeteering characters in a video game environment. It was very precise work, and we had to be extremely in tune to get the shots right. And it was tremendous fun; several of my closest friends these days are people I met on the &lt;em&gt;BloodSpell&lt;/em&gt; shoot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, I&amp;rsquo;ve always loved directing actors in voice acting and motion capture. And physical filmmaking is like a combination of those two things. It&amp;rsquo;s extremely collaborative. It&amp;rsquo;s constantly challenging, which is indeed a euphemism for &amp;lsquo;things are always going wrong&amp;rsquo;, but I love that sort of environment. It brings a bunch of very smart people together to make something cool, and pushes all of us to solve problems together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you haven&amp;rsquo;t tried it, I recommend doing so. It&amp;rsquo;s awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;addenda-more-points-needing-less-write-up&#34;&gt;Addenda: more points needing less write-up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;People are super-used to video noise these days.&lt;/strong&gt; Non-experts will be more forgiving of it than you&amp;rsquo;d expect. I was worried about the noise on some of my shots, but I&amp;rsquo;ve had exactly zero comments on it, &lt;em&gt;even when I specifically asked about video noise&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Your crew aren&amp;rsquo;t on the same diet as you&lt;/strong&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m on Paleo, and as such I had completely forgotten that milk and sugar exist. My (British) crew reminded me of this in no uncertain terms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We lost SOOOO much time to me losing lens caps&lt;/strong&gt;. Much as I love my lightweight shooting, roles have evolved inside the film industry for a reason, and I rapidly figured out why the &amp;lsquo;camera assistant&amp;rsquo; position exists. Now I&amp;rsquo;m very, very careful where I put my lens caps, and I still haven&amp;rsquo;t had a shoot where I haven&amp;rsquo;t temporarily lost a lens cap yet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lines are harder to learn if they&amp;rsquo;re in another language&lt;/strong&gt;. We spent about 3 hours on Johnnie&amp;rsquo;s magical chanting as he attempted to jam my authentic R&amp;rsquo;lyehian chant into his head. In the end, we cheated – I recorded myself reciting the chant, and Johnnie listened to it via an earbud while shooting that scene.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The traditional description of film lighting is &amp;lsquo;painting with light&amp;rsquo;&lt;/strong&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m now of the opinion that&amp;rsquo;s wrong: it should be &lt;strong&gt;painting with shadow&lt;/strong&gt;. Shadows were definitely the thing I screwed up most in the &lt;em&gt;HOWTO&lt;/em&gt; lighting. There were way too many bright white walls.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pre-production is huge&lt;/strong&gt;. I could do an entire post about this. Suffice it to say that my rule for short film shoot prep is now to assume it&amp;rsquo;ll take at least 3 days longer than I expect – even after I&amp;rsquo;ve taken this rule into account.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I saw a lot of film makers complaining about camera gimbals&lt;/strong&gt; (robotised support mechanisms, like a twenty-first-century Steadicam) that required tools. I didn&amp;rsquo;t really understand why it was such an issue. Now I do. On a shoot, time used for &lt;strong&gt;anything&lt;/strong&gt; is super-important, and setting up my gimbal, a Nebula 4000, took 15 minutes we didn&amp;rsquo;t have. I now own a toolless gimbal.  :)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;And that&amp;rsquo;s it! Any comments, thoughts, or questions? Any ways I could have done things better? Let me know on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.twitter.com&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/strangecompany&#34;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; or just &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.strangecompany.org/contact/&#34;&gt;email me&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why The Guy Who Coined &#34;Machinima&#34; Is Now Making Live-Action Films</title>
      <link>http://www.strangecompany.org/why-the-guy-who-coined-machinima-is-now-making-live-action-films/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2015 14:32:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.strangecompany.org/why-the-guy-who-coined-machinima-is-now-making-live-action-films/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I made my first Machinima – in-game animation – film in 1997. That was three years before I coined a word – Machinima – to describe the weird animation stuff I was doing, based on the suggestion of fellow Machinima pioneer Anthony Bailey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I worked in the medium between then and 2014. But now, a year later, I&amp;rsquo;ve got 4 story projects going and none of them is Machinima. On Monday, I release my first ever live-action (fiction) film, &lt;em&gt;HOWTO: Demon Summoning&lt;/em&gt; ( click here to get updated when it comes out ). It&amp;rsquo;s set in a world of Lovecraftian horrors and disgruntled techies, it uses a lot of technology I developed in Machinima, but it&amp;rsquo;s not Machinima.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.strangecompany.org/media/Machinima_To_Film.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Machinima_To_Film&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of it is that Machinima falls uncomfortably between the &amp;ldquo;film&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;game&amp;rdquo; stools, which causes problems of its own. That&amp;rsquo;s something I&amp;rsquo;ll talk about another time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the main reason is that it feels like film – or, more accurately, digital video – is finally taking up the mantle which I felt Machinima alone held for so long: that of a truly democratic filmic medium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not so much that Machinima got worse; it&amp;rsquo;s that film got far, far better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-do-i-mean-by-a-democratic-medium&#34;&gt;What Do I Mean By A Democratic Medium?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But wasn&amp;rsquo;t film democratised way back when, in the early 2000s or even the late 90s?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not at all. It became &lt;strong&gt;more&lt;/strong&gt; accessible, certainly. Digital video opened up the possibility of creating a feature film to thousands of people who couldn&amp;rsquo;t consider it before. But it still had a long way to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason for the massive glut of indie horror movies and &amp;lsquo;mumblecore&amp;rsquo; films – naturalistic dialogue, no lighting, few characters – is that digital video was a breakthrough, but it wasn&amp;rsquo;t the only breakthrough that live-action film needed. Cameras were cheaper, tape was far cheaper than film, and non-linear editing meant you could edit your film on a home computer rather than a Steenbeck rented by the hour, but plenty of things were still slow and awkward:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lighting was a huge bugbear. Cameras required tons of light, and the only lights available were power-heavy tungstens, which would blow out ordinary 13-amp fuses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Special effects were getting more sophisticated at the high end, but they still really weren&amp;rsquo;t any more practical at a garage-band level. Photorealistic 3D rendering took forever and required extremely expensive tools.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Props and set decoration required hours or days of scouring local shops or navigating the rudimentary options online.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Moving the camera was a nightmare. You could pick it up for the Blair Witch / Paranormal Activity vomitcam look, or you could stick it on a tripod. But if you wanted to do long, sophisticated moving shots, you were looking at a Hollywood budget again.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consumer or prosumer digital video cameras still weren&amp;rsquo;t capable of film quality. They didn&amp;rsquo;t have interchangeable lenses, and they didn&amp;rsquo;t produce footage that looked as nice as film.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Fix it in post&amp;rdquo; was still a phrase cursed in the industry. You could do wonders with film thanks to new digital tools – but those digital tools were expensive, slow and unreliable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was possible to make &lt;strong&gt;a film&lt;/strong&gt; for very little money, and have it stand up – but not any film. The film had to be very precisely tailored for the medium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could tell a story, &lt;strong&gt;but not any story&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that&amp;rsquo;s the reason I went into Machinima, made my first feature film using the medium, engaged Brian Blessed and Joanna Lumley to make a WoW movie, and so on. I was fully aware of digital video, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to either massively restrict my stories or go into the traditional movie death spiral of endless fundraising and zero filmmaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;in-2015-the-barriers-are-lifting&#34;&gt;In 2015, The Barriers Are Lifting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those barriers, and the many other problems in live-action film, certainly haven&amp;rsquo;t vanished in 2015. But it feels to me like we&amp;rsquo;ve reached the tipping point, and that&amp;rsquo;s why I&amp;rsquo;m diving into real-world filmmaking at last.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Embarassingly for someone best known for doing clever things with 3D animation packages, the biggest changes have come from much simpler special effects tools. In particular &lt;em&gt;Adobe After Effects&lt;/em&gt;, the mostly-2D compositing tool, has changed filmmaking and continues to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s an example of genius pioneer Gareth Edwards&amp;rsquo; work using &lt;em&gt;After Effects&lt;/em&gt; and similar tools to create massive battles with a tiny crew. I first became aware of Edwards when Justin Hall, whom I worked with on my feature film &lt;em&gt;Bloodspell&lt;/em&gt;, edited Edwards&amp;rsquo; first feature, &lt;em&gt;Monsters&lt;/em&gt;. Subsequently, watching his work is one of the major reasons I&amp;rsquo;ve made the switch:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of simple tools come together at once to cause this tipping point – and it&amp;rsquo;s not necessarily that the tools are available now, but that they&amp;rsquo;re &lt;em&gt;evolved&lt;/em&gt; now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not just &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.strangecompany.org/experiments-part-1-virtual-sets/&#34;&gt;greenscreening&lt;/a&gt;, for example: that&amp;rsquo;s been around forever. But it&amp;rsquo;s also the evolution of greenscreening tools from massively time-intensive pains in the ass to things that I can use to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.strangecompany.org/is-gaming-culture-short-changed-by-current-intellectual-property-law/&#34;&gt;create a 15-minute lecture in a single day from greenscreen footage&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3D camera move tracking has been around forever too, but it used to be useless unless you wanted to spend a month on a single shot. Now I can take a video with my DSLR, run it through some simple software and have a Minecraft zombie walking around, perfectly synced, within half a day:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://vimeo.com/117587153&#34;&gt;Desk Zombie&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&#34;https://vimeo.com/strangecompany&#34;&gt;Strange Company&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;https://vimeo.com&#34;&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;HOWTO: Demon Summoning&lt;/em&gt; wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have been possible to make without that tech. I&amp;rsquo;d still have been tracking my handheld camera shots for my CGI character next July.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so it goes on. Lighting is one of the really big things that pushed me into live-action: where film used to require those massive, hot, dangerous lights, I can now use a Sony a7s camera capable of shooting really nice footage &lt;a href=&#34;https://vimeo.com/99893160&#34;&gt;using only the light of the stars and the moon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We shot much of &lt;em&gt;HOWTO: Demon Summoning&lt;/em&gt; by the light of 4 tealight candles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, if I need light, I can use a magic battery-powered stick – the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mvTvwQSdwQQ&#34;&gt;Westcott Icelight&lt;/a&gt; – that generates pro-photographer quality light for hours with no leads and almost no weight. That made a hell of a difference on another upcoming short, &lt;em&gt;Dangerous Treasures&lt;/em&gt;, where we had to rapidly move from room to room setting up shots, and the Icelight meant I could do that in minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where I would once have had to employ a team of sweating grips and miles of track, I can now use a gimbal: essentially, a robot which stabilises my camera and transforms wobbly handheld movements into silky-smooth dolly shots. On &lt;em&gt;HOWTO&lt;/em&gt; that let me move the camera with the same sort of freedom I&amp;rsquo;m used to having in a 3D program, rather than being limited to the old-school low-budget approach of tripod or wobbly handheld.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And where I would have had to employ props masters just to source all the weird and wonderful props I needed, I can now just search on eBay or Amazon for bizarre sacrificial knives or &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ebay.co.uk/itm/ANGLE-GLASS-LILY-PIPES-FREE-DELIVERY-MULTIPACK-/111652867184?pt=LH_DefaultDomain_3&amp;amp;var=410664499290&amp;amp;hash=item19ff078c70&#34;&gt;props for a crack pipe&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s becoming amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;and-this-is-just-the-beginning&#34;&gt;And this is just the beginning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Experienced filmmakers and videographers will be getting terribly cynical at this point. Filmmaking is, as of 2015, certainly not yet cheap, effortless or completely without budgetary constraints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tools are still finnicky and require powerful PCs. Cameras are expensive, they&amp;rsquo;ve got poor UI and they require a massive pile of support equipment. Certainly, you can make a film with a crew of two, but it&amp;rsquo;s not easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of that is true, no question. But the thing is, we&amp;rsquo;re not at the end of this journey. We&amp;rsquo;re at the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cameras are going to get smaller, faster and easier to use. MUCH smaller, faster and easier. We&amp;rsquo;re already seeing feature films shot on an iPhone which get into &lt;em&gt;Sundance&lt;/em&gt;, and this isn&amp;rsquo;t an &amp;lsquo;in spite of how they look&amp;rsquo; deal, either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was shot on an iPhone 5s. It&amp;rsquo;s universally acknowledged that the camera on the iPhone 6 is far better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a look at the future, look at GoPro. For those who aren&amp;rsquo;t aware, GoPro produce &amp;lsquo;action cameras&amp;rsquo; – incredibly ruggedised cameras designed for use by people engaging in action sports. Note that I didn&amp;rsquo;t say, &amp;lsquo;people filming people engaging in action sports&amp;rsquo;. I mean: &amp;lsquo;for use whilst you&amp;rsquo;re climbing, skydiving or otherwise doing something that really requires your full attention&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GoPro have just brought out a new camera. It&amp;rsquo;s absolutely tiny. It produces very nice footage; it&amp;rsquo;s not competing with top-end cameras, but the footage is perfectly usable for professional production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it has one button. Press to start recording, press again to stop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s the level of ease we&amp;rsquo;re heading toward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just bought a new camera to use as a B camera, and immediately used it extensively in &lt;em&gt;Dangerous Treasures&lt;/em&gt;. BTW, it&amp;rsquo;s also my phone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote a piece a month or so ago looking at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.strangecompany.org/will-your-next-cameraperson-be-a-robot-maybe-yes/&#34;&gt;rise of robot cameras&lt;/a&gt; – things that can film, move and follow action autonomously. The first generation of those will spend a lot of time crashing into trees. The seventh generation won&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re on the slope now. We&amp;rsquo;re gathering speed toward a world where making a film isn&amp;rsquo;t easy – it&amp;rsquo;ll never be easy to create good art – but it&amp;rsquo;s no harder than cracking open a copy of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.literatureandlatte.com/scrivener.php&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scrivener&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is for authors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that&amp;rsquo;s why I&amp;rsquo;m suddenly interested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to see the first example of what I can achieve with this stuff? As I said, &lt;em&gt;HOWTO: Demon Summoning&lt;/em&gt; is coming out on Monday. It&amp;rsquo;s a fun tale of a startup founder who got screwed by his colleagues, and now he&amp;rsquo;s out for revenge – with the aid of the Dark Arts, and by following a handy YouTube tutorial. What could possibly go wrong? Click here to get updated when it comes out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I&amp;rsquo;d love to hear what you think. Am I being too optimistic, or is this stuff really happening?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Do Podcasts Beat Film, Games And Comics As A Storytelling Medium?</title>
      <link>http://www.strangecompany.org/do-podcasts-beat-film-games-and-comics-as-a-medium/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jul 2015 12:40:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.strangecompany.org/do-podcasts-beat-film-games-and-comics-as-a-medium/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;A couple of weeks ago I posted my moderately ambitious piece &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.antipope.org/charlie/blog-static/2015/06/hugh-hancock-here-again-charli.html&#34;&gt;overviewing all available storytelling media in 2015&lt;/a&gt; from the point of view of a creator looking for the best possible medium in which to tell stories. And people liked it a great deal - I&amp;rsquo;ve had positive comments from all over the web, and a great deal of discussion with very intelligent folk about my conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That discussion brought up a lot of fascinating points, which I&amp;rsquo;ll be addressing in a couple of posts over here. But the most eye-opening point for me was that I&amp;rsquo;d missed an entire medium in my roundup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which medium?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.strangecompany.org/media/Podcasting-e1436183302147.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Podcasting&#34; /&gt;Podcasting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By extension, when we&amp;rsquo;re talking about podcasts as a storytelling tool we&amp;rsquo;re also talking about audio drama – a medium with a long and storied history, and one that I&amp;rsquo;ve enjoyed in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I realised I&amp;rsquo;d missed this entire medium, I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing a lot of research on podcasts and audio as a storytelling tool. This post is meant as a kind of notebook on what I&amp;rsquo;ve learned so far about the potential for this rather neglected medium in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-audience-for-audio-drama&#34;&gt;The Audience For Audio Drama&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I must admit, I hardly ever listen to podcasts, which is why I forgot them in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people seem to either listen to podcasts on their commute, or whilst doing other things. I don&amp;rsquo;t have a commute, as I&amp;rsquo;ve spent the last couple of decades making animated movies from my home office, barring occasional trips out to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.deathknightlovestory.com/behind-the-scenes/&#34;&gt;record Brian Blessed&lt;/a&gt; or impersonate a Muppet on CNN (true story). And I don&amp;rsquo;t like multitasking - it&amp;rsquo;s provably inefficient and stressful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So podcasts really don&amp;rsquo;t fit well into my lifestyle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I&amp;rsquo;m aware that they&amp;rsquo;re a huge part of a lot of peoples&amp;rsquo; lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just last year podcasting had its first truly massive breakout hit with &lt;a href=&#34;http://serialpodcast.org/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Serial&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the serialised investigation into a young woman&amp;rsquo;s murder in Baltimore in 1999. &lt;em&gt;Serial&lt;/em&gt; had hit 40,000,000 downloads by the end of 2014, with an average of 3.5 million downloads per episode – numbers that compare pretty well with cable television shows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, looking at a different area of audio drama, there&amp;rsquo;s also been a massive growth in the audiobook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, until recently the audiobook was a tiny, neglected corner of the market. In the last few years, though, thanks to smartphones, iTunes and Amazon spin-off Audible, Audiobooks have grown to be a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wsj.com/articles/SB10001424127887323854904578637850049098298&#34;&gt;billion-dollar business&lt;/a&gt;. Audiobooks range in production value from single-narrator readings – not exactly audio drama per se, but worth considering – to &amp;lsquo;multi-voiced&amp;rsquo; audiobooks, which are pushing close to being full audio dramas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of which is extremely interesting. We&amp;rsquo;re looking at another medium that has had a massive change in &lt;strong&gt;distribution&lt;/strong&gt; rather than just production in the last decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.antipope.org/charlie/blog-static/2015/06/hugh-hancock-here-again-charli.html&#34;&gt;original article&lt;/a&gt;, the only other medium that has gone through this is written fiction – which is, not coincidentally, also probably the healthiest of the available ways to tell stories. Given that audio storytelling has arguably had a bigger transformation, that&amp;rsquo;s very interesting indeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-much-does-audio-drama-cost&#34;&gt;How Much Does Audio Drama Cost?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The economics of audio are also pretty attractive. It&amp;rsquo;s at least an order of magnitude cheaper than film or television – a point brought up in a &lt;a href=&#34;http://schedule.sxsw.com/2015/events/event_FP41308&#34;&gt;SXSW panel this year on audio drama&lt;/a&gt;. Like comics and books, it&amp;rsquo;s a medium in which it is perfectly feasible for an independent creator like me to produce long-form serialised fiction. And, indeed, several creators are doing just that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.strangecompany.org/media/1424727845212.png&#34; alt=&#34;1424727845212&#34; /&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://commonplacebooks.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Welcome To Night Vale&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is one of the new school of audio drama, and probably the closest thing to a breakout hit in audio drama at this point. It&amp;rsquo;s a single-narrator show in the style of radio news, with occasional guest voice actors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.werealive.com/episodes/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re Alive&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a long-running audio drama centred around a zombie apocalypse. It&amp;rsquo;s sufficiently popular that it recently closed an Indiegogo campaign at $50,000 for a new 5-hour miniseries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That number does bring up one significant point. Whilst it&amp;rsquo;s considerably cheaper than film or television, audio drama still isn&amp;rsquo;t as cheap as comics production, written fiction or even some game design. The BBC, who are pretty much the gold standard of audio drama production at this point ( they produce &lt;em&gt;The Archers&lt;/em&gt;, the longest-running serial drama in the world and the original soap opera, as well as shorter dramas like the ground-breaking &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Lord_of_the_Rings_%281981_radio_series%29&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lord Of The Rings&lt;/em&gt; radio adaption&lt;/a&gt; ), currently budget around £23,000 per hour of radio drama.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s certainly possible to produce credible audio drama for less than that, but the costs are still non-zero, particularly if you need to hire a sound engineer to do everything from foley work to levelling and equalising audio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actors can also cost significant money. Audio recording is a lot faster than film, but it still takes significant time: working in animation I&amp;rsquo;m reasonably used to the timeframes involved, and it&amp;rsquo;s around 3–4 hours for 30 minutes of finished audio. If you&amp;rsquo;re looking at producing 5+ hours of material, that still adds up to more than a week of solid recording.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally there are hardware costs. USB microphones are pretty cheap these days – around $100 – but if you&amp;rsquo;re looking at assembling a studio for multiple actors to record in at once, you&amp;rsquo;ll need to buy a mixer and multiple XLR condenser mics, as well as stands, pop shields and other ancilliary costs. The cost of the kit isn&amp;rsquo;t back-breaking – around $1000 or so – but it&amp;rsquo;s not zero, either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;can-audio-drama-make-money-surprisingly-yes&#34;&gt;Can Audio Drama Make Money? Surprisingly, Yes.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So can you &lt;strong&gt;make&lt;/strong&gt; money? Well, like books, the answer is a very big &amp;lsquo;yes&amp;rsquo; if you&amp;rsquo;re producing non-fiction. A considerable number of businesses are now focused on or built around podcasting, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.smartpassiveincome.com&#34;&gt;Pat Flynn&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Smart Passive Income&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.entrepreneuronfire.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Entrepreneur On Fire&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in the Internet Marketing world, to folk like Joe Rogan and Jimmy Pardo, who host profitable podcast talk shows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, as previously mentioned, audiobooks are a pretty big business, although I&amp;rsquo;ve been unable to get clear figures on exactly how profitable they are for authors (anyone?) as yet. Also, audiobooks that are simply a single narrator reading are a lot cheaper to make than a full audio drama, which skews the figures if we&amp;rsquo;re talking about fully produced audio drama as opposed to simple narration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In-podcast advertising certainly pays, and at rates that would have most YouTube creators weeping into their webcams with joy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not an exaggeration to say that if video advertising rates were the equivalent of podcast advertising rates, I&amp;rsquo;d be seriously considering making video drama for streaming channels. Podcast advertising is quoted by multiple sources as being around $15 CPM – Cost Per Mille, or payout per thousand views. Given that it&amp;rsquo;s entirely possible to have multiple ads in a single podcast, figures like $60 / thousand downloads of a one hour podcast are entirely achievable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At that point, you need a large but potentially feasible audience to break even – half a million downloads or so if you&amp;rsquo;re producing to BBC standards and prices, and around 50,000–100,000 if you&amp;rsquo;re producing to a more &amp;lsquo;indie&amp;rsquo; quality. That&amp;rsquo;s still tough: &lt;em&gt;Welcome To Night Vale&lt;/em&gt; has achieved 150,000 downloads in a single week, but that was peak performance for the breakout example of the genre. However, for a professionally-produced drama with skilled marketers behind it, those numbers look feasible to me. It&amp;rsquo;s certainly not too far off numbers that Strange Company&amp;rsquo;s video productions have achieved in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, you could sell the drama, potentially packaging it more as a highly-produced audiobook. Audible are experimenting with that market themselves, having recently &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2014/12/01/business/media/new-art-form-rises-audio-without-the-book-.html&#34;&gt;commissioned an original audio drama from thriller writer Jeffery Deaver&lt;/a&gt;. Would it make a profit? It&amp;rsquo;s very hard to say without more figures from Audible and their self-publishing partners ACX. But it sounds plausible. Certainly, there&amp;rsquo;s precedent: audio drama producers &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bigfinish.com/&#34;&gt;Big Finish&lt;/a&gt; have been producing audio drama on CD for the past 20 years and, more recently, downloads for fans of UK sci-fi shows, as a commercial enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oddly enough for such an old medium – given radio dramas have been around for 100 years at this point – the new audio drama feels like a very new frontier. There aren&amp;rsquo;t a lot of people producing in the medium yet, and the atmosphere in the most popular discussion groups and blogs is very &amp;lsquo;indie&amp;rsquo; and uncommercial. Indeed, Fred Greenhalgh, one of the other pioneers of the &amp;lsquo;new audio drama&amp;rsquo;, has explicitly rejected charging for his audio dramas &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.finalrune.com/why-free/&#34;&gt;on the grounds that he&amp;rsquo;s more interested in popularising the medium than he is in profit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;to-audio&#34;&gt;To Audio?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of which adds up to&amp;hellip; what?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very promising opportunity, that&amp;rsquo;s what. We&amp;rsquo;re looking at another medium that is growing rapidly, is relatively affordable to produce and has examples of profitable production within adjacent media if not directly within podcast audio drama itself. It has the long-form potential of television without the enormous barrier to entry, and the distribution revolution of books without being&amp;hellip; well, books. (As I mentioned in the original article, I just don&amp;rsquo;t get on with writing written fiction.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m certainly intending to experiment with a short production in the near future. I&amp;rsquo;d be really fascinated to hear about any other successful work in the medium, people working on business models for it, and similar things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do you think podcasts and audio dramas are an untapped opportunity for storytellers? Do you know of examples I&amp;rsquo;ve missed? Let me know!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>